<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short analysis of a part of the second chapter of S. Iames, from the 14. verse to the end of the same With a briefe confutation of the Rhemists annotations therevpon written. By Iohn Morgan. 1588</title>
            <author>Morgan, John, fl. 1588.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107508</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843207</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 480:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short analysis of a part of the second chapter of S. Iames, from the 14. verse to the end of the same With a briefe confutation of the Rhemists annotations therevpon written. By Iohn Morgan. 1588</title>
                  <author>Morgan, John, fl. 1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin, for Edward Aggas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Rhemists annotations 2. Iames aunswered.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-C D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through; some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James II, 14-26 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James II, 14-26. --  Versions, Catholic.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Short Analyſis of a part of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter of S. Iames, from the 14. verſe to the end of the ſame.</p>
            <p>With a briefe confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Rhemistes Annotations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon written.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Morgan.</hi> 1588.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas Orwin, for Edward Aggas. 1588.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7922:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7922:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Right Honorable <hi>and VVorſhipfull Ladies, the Ladie</hi> Walſingham and Ladie Sidney: Iohn Morgan <hi>wiſheth encreaſe</hi> of all heauenly and ſpirituall grace in Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Lect and Chriſtian Ladies, as nothing is more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to our ſaluation, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more pleaſant to the inward man, renewed in knowledge, after the Image of him that created vs, then the knowledge of that high myſterie of our iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by faith only: which doctrine is euen the ſoule of the Church, agaynſt which, as Sathan hath layd all his engines, that this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial poynt of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religion, might either by force be ouerthrowne, or with ſubtiltie might be vndermined; ſo it hath pleaſed the Lord to rampire in this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine: with ſuch a fierie wal of Scriptures,
<pb facs="tcp:7922:3"/>that all the gates of hell cannot preuayle agaynſt it. But as Sathan is wont ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to transforme himſelfe into an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of light, ſo by the Scriptures he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to ouerturne the Scriptures: but yet the ſworde of the Spirite, which is the word of God, is of ſuch ſharpe edge, that it hath alwaies and will to the end cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder all the knottie quiddities, which our aduerſaries (though neuer ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly) ſhall endeuour to contriue againſt the plaine trueth, reueiled in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For experience wherof, I haue here dedicated to your Worſhips, a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of my labours, reading in my charge vpon the Epiſtle of Sainct <hi>Iames:</hi> wherein as I laboured to teach the trueth of God plainly for the capacitie of the ſimple; ſo likewiſe, as occaſion was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, according to my poore skill, I aſſaied to confute errors of ſeducing Spirites: which if it ſhall pleaſe you to accept, as willingly as I do offer the ſame vnto you duetifully, I ſhall thinke the fruite of my labours well beſtowed, to bee receiued
<pb facs="tcp:7922:3"/>into the hands, and peruſed with the eyes of two ſo vertuous and religious Ladies: and the rather I am incouraged hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, becauſe I would prouoke a freſh the eger appetites of thoſe which haue ſtaied (too long I am ſure, as they thinke) with a fore-taſt of ſome little banquetting diſh, to make them longue the more for the whole ſeruice, moſt artificially and rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I hope, ere it bee long, of thoſe to bee brought out, which are able to prouide the diet, and furniſh the prouiſion of a Princely table: who (I am ſure) will no more be offended with me for ſhaking a light Launce agaynſt the Campe of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, then worthie Generalls, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Coronels are wont with their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines for ſhewing their valure, and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſtraggler comming in his way, whoſe comming might ſomething pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice any corner of the hoaſt. And now to you, O <hi>Romiſh Rhemiſts:</hi> when wil you open your eyes to ſee the trueth? when will you take that precious <hi>Collyrium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.1</note> a ſoueraigne eye-ſalue, wherof S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,
<pb facs="tcp:7922:4"/>that you may once ſee your bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to that <hi>Italian Antichriſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you know what is meant, when will you learne to ſee the glorious libertie of the Sonnes of God? Will you be more blind then the <hi>Turkes,</hi> who though they are <hi>Agarenes,</hi> yet will be called <hi>Saracenes?</hi> But you who pretending Catholikes, the Mother Church, the ſonnes of <hi>Sarah,</hi> wil yet for all this, as though you were borne of her wombe, ioyne with <hi>Hagar.</hi> You will not be iuſtified only by grace, by the free promiſe only, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was borne, but as that luſty yonker <hi>Iſmael,</hi> you wil mock <hi>Iſaac</hi> as a <hi>Solifidian,</hi> and more then that perſecute the lawfull heires with fire and fagot; you will be borne by the ſtrength of fleſh, and not by the power of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, only: A luſtie dame muſt bee your Mother, or els you will not haue <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to be your Father: you will ioyne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with grace: O blind generation; you will not worke but for hire: you will do no good deedes, but to auoyde the whot ſcalding houſe of Purgatorie: O ſeruile
<pb facs="tcp:7922:4"/>brood. If you will not beleeue me, I pray you giue eare to that old, eloquent, good father <hi>Nazianzene. If thou be a bondſlaue,
<note place="margin">Nazian. de Sancto Bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mate.</note> then feare the whippe: if thou be an hyreling, then looke only for thy rewarde: but ouer and beſides this, if thou be a (naturall) Child, then reuerence (God) as thy Father: Do well, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is good to obey thy Father: yea, and although thou ſhalt haue nothing els, yet euen this ſhall be thy reward: that thou haſt been obedient to thy Father.</hi> Thus leauing theſe Ieſuites to bee ſchooled of ſo graue and reuerend a Father, till his fatherhood and their owne conſcience, better inſtructed, ſhall direct them, I commend your good Ladiſhips to the fatherly protection of the heauenly Father, who is the father of all mercies, and the Father of the whole familie both in heauen and earth. To whom be al praiſe and glorie aſcribed for his free and vndeſerued mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, both now and euermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moſt bounden to pray for your good Ladiſhips in the Lord. <hi>I. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:7922:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7922:5"/>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts Annotations <hi>in 2. Chap. of Iames.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Verſe. 13. Iudgement without mercie.]</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing giueth more hope of mercie in the next life, then the works of Almes, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and mercie, done to our neighbors in this life: Neither ſhall any be vſed with extreame rigour in the next world, but ſuch as vſed not mercy in this world, <hi>Aug. de peccat. merit. lib. 2. cap. 3.</hi> which is true, not only in reſpect of the iudgement to euerlaſting damnation, but alſo of the temporall chaſtiſement in Purgatorie, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſignifieth, declaring that our venial ſinnes be waſhed away in this world, with dayly works of mercy, which otherwiſe ſhould be chaſtiſed in the next, See <hi>Epiſt. 29.</hi> aforeſaid <hi>in fine,</hi> and <hi>lib. 21. De Ciuit. Dei. cap. 27. in fine.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p>COncerning the temporall chaſtiſement in Purgatorie, as the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> do place the principall buttreſſe of defence ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in <hi>S. Auguſtine.</hi> But how inconſtant <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7922:6"/>was in this error, appeareth by this, that ſometimes he doubteth whether there be any ſuch matter, other-whiles he ſeemeth plainely to deny all other receptacles of the ſoules departed, beſide heauen and hell: for both in his <hi>Enchiridion ad Laurentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 69. cap Et de octo Dulcitij in quaestionibus queſt.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſaith, That as it is not incredible, that ſuch a matter may be after this life, ſo it may be doubted whether it be ſo or no, likewiſe in his booke <hi>De fide &amp; operibus cap. 16.</hi> he hath theſe words, ſpeaking of that text of <hi>S. Paul, 1. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians 3,</hi> Therefore whether in this life only men ſuffer theſe things, either after this life ſuch iudgements do follow, it abhorreth not, <hi>for as much as I thinke,</hi> from the reaſon of truth the vnderſtanding of this ſentence. Againe, in <hi>Hypognoſt. cont. Pelagianos lib. 5,</hi> he acknowledgeth the kingdom of heauen, for to receiue the godly, &amp; hell fire for the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the wicked, but a third place ſaith he we are alltogether ignorant of, neither do we find it in the holy Scriptures. To the like effect he writeth, <hi>De verbis Apoſtoli, Sermone 14,</hi> where he acknowledgeth the right hand and the left hand of God, that is, the kingdome of heauen, &amp; the paines of hell, the middle place he vtterly denieth, wherein infants might be placed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion therof in the Goſpell.
<pb facs="tcp:7922:6"/>The foundation of Popiſh Purgatorie, is the diſtinction of mortall &amp; venial ſinnes, whereas the word of God plainly determineth, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſin is mortall, &amp; deſerueth eternall death. Curſed is euery one that abideth not in all things that are written in the Lawe, to fulfill them, <hi>Deut. 27.</hi> The ſoule that ſinneth ſhall dye, <hi>Ezek. 18.</hi> The reward of ſinne is death. And as for that diſtinction which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>cap. 5.1. Epiſt.</hi> of a ſin to death. A ſin not to death, hath nothing common with that of the Papiſts, for all ſin that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of God is pardonable, he calleth a ſin not vnto death, for which God is intreated, that giueth life to them that haue ſo ſinned: and that ſinne he counteth vnto death, which is irremiſſible, as obſtinate and wilfull apoſtacie. <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie againſt the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Math. 12,</hi> for which it is not lawfull to pray, thus by the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Gods word, are all ſins mortal, which the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> call veniall, and all that they count mortall, by Gods ſpirit are counted ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial: for by the iuſtice of God all ſins are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, but by his mercy they are all pardonable, except that ſinne vnto death, whereof <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotation">
               <head>Rhemiſts Annotat. Iames 2. verſ. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Ver. 14. What ſhall it profit, if a man ſay he hath faith.]</hi> This whole paſſage of the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:7922:7"/>is ſo cleere againſt iuſtification or ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by only faith, damnably defended by the Proteſtants, and ſo euident for the neceſsitie, merit, or concurrence of good works, that their firſt Author <hi>Luther,</hi> and ſuch as exactly follow him, boldly (after the manner of Heretikes) when they can make no ſhift, nor falſe gloſe for the text, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Booke to be Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural But <hi>Caluin</hi> and his companions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing from their miniſters, confeſſe it to be holie Scripture. But their ſhifts, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> gloſes, for anſwere of ſo plaine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, be as impudent, as the denying of the Epiſtle was in the other: who would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue denied the Booke, thereby to ſhew them-ſelues Heretikes; if they had thought thoſe vulgar euaſions that the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> do vſe (whereof they were not ignorant) could haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in both ſorts, the chriſtian Reader may ſee, that all the Heretikes, vaunting of expreſſe Scriptures, and the word of God, is no more but to delude the world: whereas indeede, be the Scriptures neuer ſo plaine againſt them, they muſt either: be wreſted to ſound as they ſay, or elſe they muſt be no Scriptures at all, and to ſee <hi>Luther, Caluin, Beza,</hi> and their felowes,
<pb facs="tcp:7922:7"/>ſit as it were in iudgement of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to allow, or diſalow at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, it is the moſt notorious example of Hereticall pride and miſerie that can be: See their Prefaces, and Cenſures vpon this Canonicall Epiſtle, the Apocalypſe, and other.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>IF the Doctrine deliuered by <hi>S. Paule,</hi> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the auntient Fathers be damnable, of our iuſtification by faith only, we haue no ſkill of ſuch ſharpe cenſures. Was it dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably vttered by <hi>Baſile, in Homil. de Humilit.</hi> This is ſound and perfect reioycing in God, when as a man is not lifted vp with his owne righteouſneſſe, but knoweth him-ſelfe to be voyde of true iuſtice, but to be iuſtified by <hi>faith alone in Chriſt:</hi> for verely, to beleeue alone, is righteouſnes. And <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> Take away your merit,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> and as for the neceſſitie and concurrence of good works, we yeeld that good works are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to ſaluation, and the fruits of faith, do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes concurre, that a good trée doth bring forth good fruits. If they be to be counted He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes which haue doubted of the authoritie of this Epiſtle, <hi>Euſebius</hi> then <hi>lib. 2. cap. 23.</hi> counting the ſame in plaine words, a Baſtard:
<pb facs="tcp:7922:8"/>
                     <hi>Luther</hi> then hath a companion with him in this his opinion. The Councell of <hi>Laodicea, cap. 59.</hi> did leaue the booke of Reuelation out of the number of Canonicall bookes. <hi>Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Alexandrinus</hi> writeth, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>lib. 7. cap. 25.</hi> that many of his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors vtterly refuſed &amp; reiected the booke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation. Now if that which you obiect againſt <hi>Luther</hi> were true, his error therin, common to him with others, muſt neither preiudice the authoritie of that Epiſtle, nor the credit of thoſe who reuerence the ſame as a portion of Gods word, reade it, and expound it in their Churches. Who haue wreſted the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, you, or we, might heere be at large ſet downe to your ſhame: the gloſes of the <hi>Zuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> and <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> as you call them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in do they differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your Angelicall <hi>Thomas</hi> vpon this chapter, or the ordinarie gloſſe vpon this ſcripture, ſaying that <hi>Abraham</hi> was iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified without works by only faith, but yet the offering of his ſome was a teſtimonie of his faith and righteouſneſſe. Nay, it is not <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> that ſit as Iudges vpon the Scriptures, to allow or diſalow at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. <hi>Ambroſe Catharine</hi> vpon the Epiſtle <hi>ad Galat. cap. 2,</hi> It is the <hi>Popes</hi> proper priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to canonize Scriptures, or to reproue Scriptures: this indéed is the moſt notorious
<pb facs="tcp:7922:8"/>example of hereticall pride and miſerie, that can be: whereas you bid vs ſee the Prefaces of <hi>Luther</hi> and others, I referre you to <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Preface before his works, and there you ſhall ſée the modeſtie of <hi>Luthers</hi> ſpirit. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, I pray the Godly Reader, and beſéech him, for our Lord Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, that he would reade theſe things with iudgement, nay rather with much pitie, and let him knowe that ſometimes I was a Monke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts Annotation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Verſe. 21. Abraham was he not iustified by workes?]</hi> It is much to be noted, that <hi>S. Augustine</hi> in his booke <hi>De fide &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, cap. 14.</hi> writeth, that the Hereſie of only faith iuſtifying or ſauing, was an old Hereſie in the Apoſtles time, gathered by the falſe interpretation of ſome of <hi>S. Paules</hi> profound diſputation, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> wherein, hee commended ſo highly the faith in Chriſt, that they thought good workes were not auayleable: adding further, that the other three Apoſtles, <hi>Iames, Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Iude,</hi> did of purpoſe wright ſo mutch of good workes, to correct
<pb facs="tcp:7922:9"/>the ſaid error of only faith, gathered by the miſconſtruction of S. Paules words: yea when <hi>S. Peter, Epiſt. 2. cap. 3.</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the faithfull, that many things be hard in S. Paules writings, and of light vnlearned men miſtaken to their perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The ſayd <hi>S. Augustine</hi> affirmeth, that he meant of his diſputation concerning faith, which ſo many Heretikes did miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to condemne good works: and in his Preface of his Commentarie vpon the 31. Pſalme, he warneth all men, that this deduction vpon S. Paules ſpeach: <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was iuſtified by faith, therfore works be not neceſſarie to ſaluation, is the right way to hell and damnation. And laſtly, (which is in it ſelfe verie plaine) that we may ſee, this Apoſtle did purpoſely thus commend vnto vs, the neceſsitie of good works, and the inanity and inſufficiencie of only faith to correct the error of ſuch as miſconſtrued S. Paules words for the ſame. The ſayd holie Doctor, <hi>lib. 83. q. 9. 76.</hi> noteth that of purpoſe he tooke the verie ſame example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whome S. Paule ſayd to be iuſtified by faith, and declareth that he was iuſtified by good workes, ſpecifying the good worke for which he was iuſtified, and bleſſed of
<pb facs="tcp:7922:9"/>God, to wit, his obedience and immola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his only Sonne. But how S. Paule ſaith that Abraham was iuſtified by faith, ſee the Annotations vppon that place, <hi>Rom. 4. verſe. 1.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>YOur note out of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> is not worth the noting, for any thing that our doctrine can be thereby touched: for <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in that place writeth againſt the wicked opinion of thoſe, who miſtaking <hi>S. Paules</hi> words of iuſtification by faith without works, do by an euill ſecuritie neglect to liue well, not ſeeking by true faith the helpe of God, to the ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of their owne euill concupiſcences, but do deſpiſe the works of righteouſnes, and by a dead faith do promiſe to them-ſelues euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life: theſe be <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> expreſſe words in that place truly tranſlated, which you haue moſt vntruly and malitiouſly allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt vs, and againſt the hereſie (as you tearme it) of iuſtification by faith only, and did vtterly caſt away all care of good works, &amp; godly life, as they did againſt whome <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> did write, whereas we by faith onely iuſtifying vs, meane not to exclude the doing, but the merits of our good works. As for the Heretikes, which did miſtake the Scriptures,
<pb facs="tcp:7922:10"/>and out of the wholſome words of <hi>S. Paule,</hi> did like Spiders ſucke poyſonfull iuyce, the ſame being turned into their owne infected nature, we accurſe them to the pit of hell: And as for <hi>Libertines</hi> which turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, we ſay with <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine:</hi> How farre therefore are they deceiued, which promiſe them-ſelues life by a dead faith: The vanitie and inſufficiencie of onely faith, as <hi>Iames</hi> this bleſſed Apoſtle meaneth, we all graunt. For, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaieth, <hi>De Grat. &amp; liber. Arbitr. cap. 7.</hi> Men not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that which the Apoſtle faieth, wee déeme a man to bee iuſtified by faith without the workes of the law: they thought he ſayd, that faith was ynough for a man albeit he liue ill, and haue no good workes. In the ſame place by you cited, <hi>lib. 83. quaeſt. 76.</hi> he giueth righteouſnes to faith, he taketh away the ſame from workes. Therefore whereas the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in <hi>Iames</hi> ſaieth, <hi>Abraham</hi> was iuſtified by his workes, he ſheweth thereby, that he was indued not with a vaine and imaginarie, but with a true and ſound faith and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that by his deedes he was declared, truely to haue been a righteous man: we giue vnto workes as much as by the Scripture we haue learned, ought to be yeelded: We do not of our workes frame a new Chriſt vnto our
<pb facs="tcp:7922:10"/>ſelues, that we ſhould hope by their merites to be made righteous, and to obteyne by them the heauenly life. Theſe workes, this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, this heauen, wee willingly leaue to you and your fellowes, who ſeeke to bee iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. If you had well marked <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in his proface vpon <hi>Pſal. 31. Iames</hi> (ſayth he) in his Epiſtle, agaynſt them, which would do no good workes, preſuming of only faith, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the workes of <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelfe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Jesuits_annotations">
               <head>And becauſe the Ieſuites referre vs to Rom. cap. 4. verſ. 1. I will ſet downe their words.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Verſ. 1. Abraham]</hi> The Apoſtle diſputing in this Chapter, as before, againſt them that thought they might bee iuſtified by their works, done without the grace of Chriſt and faith in him, propoſeth <hi>Abraham</hi> for an example, and proueth that he had no iuſtice, nor eſtimation of iuſtice before God, by any workes done before he had faith, and Gods grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>TO the intent your cauilling may the more appeare, you ſay in this place the Apoſtle diſputeth agaynſt them that thought they might be iuſtified by their workes, done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the grace of Chriſt. But the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:7922:11"/>in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galathians</hi> auoucheth in the <hi>5. Chap.</hi> agaynſt them, which ioyned the workes of the law with the faith of Chriſt. In <hi>4. verſ.</hi> You are made voyde of Chriſt who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer are iuſtified by the law, and ye are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from grace. And the Apoſtle vſing the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the Prophet <hi>Abacuk 2. Chapter verſ. 4. Rom. 1. verſ. 17.</hi> and <hi>Galathians 3. verſ. 11.</hi> to proue that wee are not iuſtified by the workes of the law not after faith: for ſo he frameth the argument to the <hi>Galat.</hi> That no man is iuſtified by the law with God, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt; becauſe the iuſt ſhall liue by faith: but the law is not of faith, and ſo doth <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> interpret <hi>Paule</hi> in <hi>
                        <hi>Galat. 3.</hi> Ostendit quod fides iustificet, teſtimonio Prophetae A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacuk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts Roman. 4. verſ. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>By workes.]</hi> If <hi>Abraham</hi> did any commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable workes before he beleeued Chriſt, as many Philoſophers did, men might count him iuſt therefore: But in Gods ſight (who accepteth nothing without faith in him, of that proceedeth not from his grace) he ſhould neuer haue had the eſtimation of a iuſt man. Therefore God in the Scripture reputing him as a iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:7922:11"/>man, giueth the cauſe thereof, ſaying: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> beleeued God, and it was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for iuſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>ALL your ſhiftes cannot elude ſo playne Scripture, <hi>
                        <hi>Maledicta gloſſa quae corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit textum:</hi> S. Paule</hi> is fitteſt to expound his owne meaning, <hi>Galat. 3. verſ. 8.</hi> But the Scripture foreſeeing that God would iuſtifie the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by faith, preached the Goſpell vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> before, ſaying: in thee ſhall all the Nations be bleſſed. <hi>verſ. 9.</hi> Therfore they which are of faith are bleſſed with faithfull <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham: Abraham</hi> beleeued God, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him for iuſtice. <hi>Ergo,</hi> his faith alone did ſaue him, neither his workes before, nor after.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts Annotat. Rom. 4. verſ. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>To him that worketh]</hi> That is to ſay, he that preſumeth of his owne works, as done of himſelfe, without faith, Gods helpe, and grace: and ſaying that grace or iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were giuen to him for his workes; this man doth chalenge his iuſtification as debt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7922:12"/>
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>WHo do preſume of their owne workes: but they which ſay by their works pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of grace, they do deſerue or merit hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and that ſay their works can bee none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the valure, deſert, price, worth, and merite of the ioyes of heauen: as in your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat. <hi>1. Cor. 3. verſ. 8.</hi> you haue ſet downe: who do chalenge their iuſtification as debt: but the Popiſh Diuines, whoſe generall doctrine of their Schooles theſe late yeeres hath been: Euerlaſting life is a reward due for our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites: euerlaſting life, except it were a due debt, it were vncertaine; becauſe hire is certaine, mercie is vncertaine. But confound grace and workes as you will, and compound with <hi>S. Paule</hi> if you cau, <hi>Rom. 11. verſ. 6.</hi> If it be of grace, not now of workes: otherwiſe now grace is not grace: but if of works, not now of grace, otherwiſe the worke now were not worke. Thus I haue ſeene a little according to your direction your Annot. <hi>Rom. 4. verſ. 1.</hi> Now to follow you in <hi>S. Iames.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts. Cap. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Verſ. 22. Faith did worke with]</hi> Some Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes hold that good workes are perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to Saluation &amp; iuſtification: other, that though they be not hurtfull but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,
<pb facs="tcp:7922:12"/>yet they be no cauſes or workers of Saluation; much leſſe meritorious, but are as fruits and effects iſſuing neceſſarily out of faith. Both which fictions, falſhods and flights from the plaine truth of Gods word, are refuted by theſe wordes, when the Apoſtle ſayth, that faith worketh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with good works, maketh faith to bee a coadiutour or Cooperator with works, and ſo both ioyntly concurring as cauſes, and workers of iuſtification: yea afterward he maketh workes the more principal cauſe, when he reſembleth faith to the bodie, and workes to the ſpirite or life of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>IT were to bée wiſhed that you had nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe Heretikes, that wee might haue knowne them by their names. If any haue ſayd their workes are imperfect, and ſo perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious for any man to place his confidence of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life in his maimed and ſtayned obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, they haue ſuch partners as you ſhall not for ſo ſaying bee able to attach of hereſie. <hi>S. Paule</hi> when as he abounded with moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent workes, he denyed that hée obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned righteouſneſſe or life thereby. <hi>1. Cor. cap. 4. verſ. 4.</hi> Neither would he reioyce in
<pb facs="tcp:7922:13"/>any thing but in the croſſe of Chriſt, <hi>
                        <hi>Galath. 6. verſ. 14.</hi> Hieroni. in Eſaiam, cap. 64,</hi> If we behold our owne merits, we muſt be driuen to deſperation. And <hi>Origen</hi> vpon <hi>Math. Tract. 8,</hi> Say that you are vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants (ſaith Chriſt) for notwithſtanding we haue done all things that are commaunded, yet haue we done no good thing: for if our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were good indéede, then were they not vnprofitable: but any good déede of ours is called good, not rightly or duly, but by abuſe of ſpeach. We ſay flatly, maugre the Deuill and Antichriſt, that our works be not cauſes or workers of our ſaluation, much leſſe meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious. <hi>Rom. 9. verſ. 16,</hi> It is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath mercy. <hi>1. Tim. 2. verſ. 5.6.</hi> There is one God, and one mediator of God and men, the man Chriſt Ieſus, who hath giuen him-ſelfe the price of redemption for vs: but if our works imbrued and drenched in the bloud of Chriſt, can pacifie the wrath of God, or make perfect our redemption, it is manifeſt there is not one mediator and redeemer, when as euery man is redeemed by his owne works. What blaſphemie is this to ſay, or once to thinke, that Chriſt ſuffered death, and poured out his bloud, not that he him-ſelfe ſhould ſaue vs by his bloud, but that he ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:7922:13"/>giue the ſame power to our works: that which you call fictions, falſehoods, and flights, ſhal be prooued to be the fixed, faithfull, firme truth of God. Doth not <hi>S. Peter</hi> in the <hi>15.</hi> of the <hi>Acts</hi> giue this vnto faith, to purifie our hearts, <hi>verſ. 9.</hi> Doth not the ſame Apoſtle <hi>2. Epiſt. cap. 1. verſ. 5.</hi> make vertue, knowledge, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, patience, brotherly kindneſſe, lone, the fruits and effects of our faith, after that by the preaching of the Goſpell, and the ſpirit of God, we are made partakers of the diuine nature, <hi>verſ. 4.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> doth not refute this doctrine by theſe words, faith wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth together with good works, no more then <hi>S. Paule</hi> doth confute his owne doctrine, when he ſaith, <hi>Galath. 5. verſ. 6.</hi> faith working by loue: thereby declaring, that a true faith is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall, and fertil of good works. If you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your marginall note vpon the <hi>4. cap. Rom. verſ. 2.</hi> Iuſtice before man, and Iuſtice before God, we graunt faith to be a coadiutor or cooperator with works, and ſo both iointly concurring as cauſes, and workers of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation before men: but if you come before God, take your aunſwere of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> in <hi>
                        <hi>Pſalm. 94.</hi> Si Deus vellet pro merit is agere, non inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niret, niſi quod damnaret.</hi> If God would deale with vs according to that we haue deſerued, he ſhould find nothing but that he might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne.
<pb facs="tcp:7922:14"/>In that which you ioyne afterwards, whereas you ſay: yea afterward he maketh works the more principall cauſe, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth faith to the body, and works to the life or ſpirit of a man. The Lord open your eyes, that you may ſee this myſterie, &amp; remeur this vaile from your eyes, of the confidence of your works. We proteſt before God and all good men, that we neuer meant to make faith the chiefe &amp; only cauſe of our iuſtification, but that the grace and mercy of God by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, promiſed to the faithfull in his holy word, is the principall &amp; originall cauſe, and very fountaine of our iuſtification, and that faith not a dead faith (as they thought againſt whome <hi>S. Iames</hi> wrote) but a liuely faith being wrought in our harts by the word of God, and by the operation of the holy Ghoſt beleuing Gods promiſe of his mercy in Chriſt is the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall cauſe in vs, whereby only we receiue our iuſtification, without the merit of out works, &amp; yet being iuſtified we are moſt hounden in all good works as much as it ſhall pleaſe God to giue vs grace thereunto. I can but muze at your folly, which make works the more principall cauſe of our iuſtification, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he reſembleth faith to the bodie, and good works to the ſoule: if either you had knowne the true ſcope of this Scripture, or the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:7922:14"/>of an argument drawne from likeneſſe, <hi>Omnis ſimilitudo claudicat,</hi> you would not haue argued ſo fondly. <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſpeaketh of a dead faith, which is only an imaginarie, and mathematicall phantaſie, which is as farre different from a true chriſtian faith, as is a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard from a mans face, an image from a man, a painted ſmoke from a burning flambe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts Annotation. Iam. 2. ver. 23.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>The friend of God]</hi> By this alſo another falſe and friuolous euaſion of the Heretikes is ouertaken when they feine, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle heere when he ſaith, works do iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, meaneth that they ſhew vs iuſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, and auaile not to our iuſtice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, for the Apoſtle euidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, that <hi>Abraham</hi> by his works was made or truly called, the friend of God, and therefore was not (as the Heretikes ſay) by his works approued iuſt before man only.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>OUr true expoſition, howſoeuer it ſéeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you a falſe and friuolous euaſion, yet I hope all that haue vſed that diſtinction are not Heretikes, for then is the Angell an Heretike, which ſo hath taught vs, <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis 22. verſ. 12.</hi> Now haue I tried that thou feareſt God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou haſt not withdrawen
<pb facs="tcp:7922:15"/>from me it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> only begotten ſonne: as if he ſhould ſay, by this déede was <hi>Abraham</hi> iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, becauſe he teſtified. that he did truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in God, and by that meanes as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle faith, the Scripture was fulfilled, and all did perceiue it for to be true, that he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in God, and that this was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts Annotat. Iames 2. verſ. 24.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Not by faith only.]</hi> This propoſition or ſpeach is directly oppoſite, or contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie to that which the Heretikes hold. For the Apoſtle ſaith, man is iuſtified by good works, and not by faith only, but the Heretikes ſay man is not iuſtified by good works, but by faith only: neither can they pretend that there is the like contradiction or contrarietie, betwixt <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſpeach, and <hi>S. Paules.</hi> For though <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſay, man is iuſtified by faith, yet he neuer ſaith by faith only, nor euer meaneth by that faith which is alone, but alwayes by that faith which worketh by charitie, Gal. 5. as he there expoundeth himſelfe. Though concerning works alſo, there is a difference betwixt the firſt iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, whereof <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpecially ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and the ſecond iuſtification, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:7922:15"/>of <hi>S. Iames</hi> doth more ſpecially treate, of which thing elſe-where there is ynough ſaid, ſee <hi>Annot. Rom. 2. ver. 13.</hi> The Fathers indeede ſometimes vſe this excluſiue <hi>Sola,</hi> only, but in far other ſenſe then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, for ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereby exclude only the works of Moſes law, againſt the Iewes, ſome the works of nature and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vertues, without the grace or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, againſt the Gentiles, ſome the neceſsitie of externall good works, where the parties lack time and means to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as in the caſe of the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theef, ſome the falſe opinions, ſects, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, contrary to the Catholike faith, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt heretiks, and miſcreants: ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude reaſon, ſenſe, &amp; arguing in matters of faith &amp; miſterie, againſt ſuch as will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue nothing, but that they ſee or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: ſome the merits of works done in ſinne before the firſt iuſtification: ſome the arrogant Phariſaicall vaunting of mans owne proper works and iuſtice, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as referre not their actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and good deeds to Gods grace. To theſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the holy Doctors ſay ſometimes, that only faith ſaueth and ſerueth: but neuer as the Proteſtants would haue it, to exclude fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtification and ſaluation, the
<pb facs="tcp:7922:16"/>cooperation of mans free will, diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; preparations of our hearts, by praiers, penance, and ſacraments, the vertues of hope &amp; charity, the purpoſe of well-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and of the obſeruation of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, much leſſe the works and merits of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, proceeding of grace and charitie, after they be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and are now in his fauour, which are not only diſpoſitions and preparations to iuſtice, but the meritorious cauſe of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iuſtice and ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>YOu would faine make vs oppoſite or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictorie to S. <hi>Iames,</hi> but neuer ſhall you bring it to paſſe, till you haue made <hi>S. Iames</hi> contrary to <hi>S. Paule:</hi> the principall ſhew of your reaſoning conſiſteth heerein, for though <hi>S. Paule</hi> (as you ſay) do affirme that a man is iuſtified by faith, yet he neuer ſaith by faith on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If we can proue that by neceſſary illation, this word only is implied in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles words then either you ſhalbe compelled to confeſſe <hi>S. Paul</hi> to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictory to <hi>S. Iames,</hi> or elſe to accord with <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> or rather w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>S. Iames</hi> himſelf by his own diſcourſe opening his own words. Now to proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>S. Paul</hi> did mean faith only, I pray you to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe reaſons out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Apoſtle himſelf. <hi>Paul</hi> doth couple nothing
<pb facs="tcp:7922:16"/>with faith in this buſines, therfore he teacheth that faith alone is ſufficient. For if it haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing coupled with it, in iuſtifying of vs, then it is manifeſt, that faith alone doth iuſtifie vs: for whatſoeuer may ſéeme any thing at all to iuſtifie vs, that altogether is remoued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith in iuſtification, for what might a man think to be ioyned with faith in this cauſe: I deeme, he will ſay works: therfore if works be diſioined, it remaineth, and that neceſſarie, that we are iuſtified by faith alone. Heere therefore <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaking in his owne words, <hi>Rom. 3.28.</hi> we gather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man is iuſtified <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, without the works of the law. And againe, he which worketh not, but beléeueth him which iuſtifieth the vngodly, his faith is imputed for righteouſnes. <hi>Rom. 4. ver. 5.</hi> Againe therefore by the works of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law ſhal no fleſh be iuſtified in his ſight. <hi>Rom. 3. ver. 20.</hi> Againe, euen as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth pronounce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man to be bleſſed, to whome God doth impute righteouſnes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, <hi>Rom. 4. ver. 6.</hi> And in another E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle more clerely, knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man is not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt: what could be ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more could confirme our ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or meaning: for if not by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> works of the law but by faith we are iuſtified, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> muſt needs folow, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are iuſtified by faith alone:
<pb facs="tcp:7922:17"/>Héereunto may be added, that he writeth we are iuſtified freely, and by the gift of God: for by grace (ſaith the Apoſtle) ye are ſaued by faith, and that not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt, <hi>Epheſ. 2. verſ. 8.9.</hi> And in another place, they are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified freely through his grace. <hi>
                        <hi>Gratis eius gratia,</hi> Rom. 3. verſ. 24.</hi> It theſe things do not ſatiſfie you, then I pray you anſwere me this argument, If we be not iuſtified by the works of the law, if to him which worketh not, but iuſtifieth the vngodly, his faith is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for righteouſneſſe: If by the works of the law no man is iuſtified, If righteouſneſſe be imputed without workes, if freely, if of grace, if by the gift of God, to conclude, if we are not iuſtified but by faith: Then we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith alone: The Antecedent is true, therefore the conſequent we graunt, though faith only iuſtifie, yet is not faith alone. But as a Queene accompanied with her maides of Honor, is only Queene, and yet not alone hauing her traine wayting vpon her: and as the eye in the bodie ſeeth only, and yet not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, without the reſt of the members, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though faith only iuſtifie, yet ſhe is not alone, but hath hope, charitie, patience attending vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her as hand-maids, to do the will of her God. Concerning your firſt &amp; ſecond iuſtification,
<pb facs="tcp:7922:17"/>
                     <hi>S. Paule</hi> neuer knew any ſuch diſtinction: for <hi>Galat. 2.</hi> after his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion <hi>verſ. 20.</hi> And the life which I now liue in the fleſh, I liue by the faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God, who hath loued me, &amp; giuen him-ſelfe for me. As this iuſtification by faith was firſt, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle maketh it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter, reſting only in that, not ſeeking any ſecond. It is well the light of truth hath ſo far-foorth ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto you, that you could find in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fathers this <hi>Excluſiue ſola</hi> only: For otherwiſe <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> would haue conuinced your folie, <hi>in Epiſt. Rom. cap. 3. lib. 3. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eſt gloriatio tua? Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa eſt: Dicit ſufficere ſolius fidei iuſtificationem.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Heſychius <hi>in Leuiticum. lib.</hi> 4.</hi> The grace of God is giuen only of fauour, and is receiued and embraced by only faith. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> vpon the Epiſtle <hi>Galat. cap. 3. <hi>Illi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebant, qui ſola fide nititur: execrabilis eſt, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi> The falſe Apoſtles ſayd, whoſoeuer ſtayeth himſelfe by only faith, is accurſed: Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>S. Paule,</hi> that whoſoeuer ſtayeth himſelf by only faith is bleſſed. Theſe with others are witneſſes of our ſound, and Catholike doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of our iuſtification by faith only: as theſe Fathers are playne in this poynt, ſo contrarie to their manifeſt wordes, you would forge an other ſenſe. The falſe Apoſtles among the <hi>Galathians</hi> did not ſhut out grace nor Chriſt: but as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> before alleadged teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth,
<pb facs="tcp:7922:18"/>that the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule</hi> iudged them to be bleſſed which ſtayed vpon faith only. I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not your inſtance of the theefe, whom you make emptie of good workes, whoſe faith in that moſt ſhort time, was vnſpeakablie effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, in making it ſelfe manifeſt by good workes, for he reproued the blaſphemies and wickedneſſe of the other theefe, he deteſted his former offences, with an aſſured and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a marueilous faith, in the very ignominie of the Croſſe, all the reſt of the Diſciples hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their peace, he acknowledgeth Chriſt to be an euerlaſting king, and calleth vpon him as a Sauiour: but the acknowledging of ſin, the inuocation of God the Father in Chriſt, and giuing of thanks are moſt excellent works of the firſt Table. Likewiſe, in-the Phariſie what can you reproue, wherein your ſelues are not to be reprehended: he vaunted of his works, you boaſt of your merites: he bragged of his kéeping of ſome parte of the lawe, you glorie in your workes of ſupererogation, that you fulfill all the meaſure of obedience due to God, with an ouer plus of righteouſneſſe: he aſcribed all this to the grace of God: you ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate part to your freewill. As in this your gloſe you talke of the cooperation of your frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. Your preparations, whereas <hi>S. Paule 2. Cor. 3. verſ. 5.</hi> ſaieth: that wee are meete it
<pb facs="tcp:7922:18"/>is of God: <hi>Philip. 2. verſ. 13.</hi> For it is God that worketh in you, both the wil and the déed, according to his frée good wil. <hi>1. Cor. 12. ver. 3</hi> No man can ſay the Lord Ieſus, but by the ſpirit of God. If the Phariſie were now aliue, he would ſhake you by the hands as his you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brethren, you Ieſuites, hearing you thus to rufflle, not onely in your diſpoſitions and preparations to iuſtice, but much more if the ſound of the meritorious cauſe of your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iuſtice and ſaluation by the Trumpet of your Annotations might come to his eares.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Verſ. 25. Rahab.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Apoſtle alleadgeth the good workes of Rahab, by which ſhe was iuſtified: and S. Paule <hi>(11. Hebrewes)</hi> ſayth, ſhe was iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith: which are not contrarie one to the other; for both is true, that ſhe was ſaued by faith, as one ſayth, and that ſhe was ſaued by her workes, as the other ſaith. But it were vntruely ſayd, that ſhe was ſaued, either by only faith, as the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes ſay: or by only good works, as no Catholik ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer ſayd. But becauſe ſome Iewes &amp; Gentil Philoſophers, did affirme; they: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould be ſaued by the works of Moſes law. Theſe, by their moral works
<pb facs="tcp:7922:19"/>Therefore S. Paule to the Romans diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpecially agaynſt both: prouing that no workes done without or before the faith of Chriſt, can ſerue to iuſtification or ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>YOur marginall note is the abridgement of your whole Annotation. <hi>S. Paule</hi> nameth faith, and <hi>S. Iames</hi> workes, cauſes of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: but neither the one, faith only, nor the other, workes only. I aunſwer, <hi>S. Paule</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med faith, as the inſtrumentall cauſe of our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, but the efficient cauſe he nameth the grace of GOD, as he reſtifieth <hi>Epheſ. 2. verſ. 8.</hi> for you are ſaued by grace through faith, and not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God. And <hi>S. Iames</hi> maketh workes as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of iuſtification. <hi>S. Paule</hi> diſputed not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agaynſt vnbeleeuing <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Gentill</hi> Philoſophers, but agaynſt beleeuing <hi>Iewes</hi> that beleeued in Chriſt, and ioyned with grace the Ceremonies of the law, yea and the moral workes of righteouſneſſe: to whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth <hi>Galat. 5. verſ. 4.</hi> Ye are made voyde of Chriſt whoſoeuer are iuſtified by the law, and ye are fallen from grace.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <pb facs="tcp:7922:19"/>
               <head>Rhemiſts Annotation verſ. 26.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Faith without workes is dead.] S. Iames</hi> (as the Proteſtants fayne) ſayth that faith without good works, is no faith, and that therefore it iuſtifieth not, becauſe it is no faith. For he ſayth that it is dead without workes, as the bodie is dead without the ſoule; and therefore being dead hath no actiuitie or efficacie to iuſtifie or ſaue. But it is a great difference, to ſay, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is dead, and to ſay, it is no bodie: euen ſo it is the like difference, to ſay that faith without workes is dead, and to ſay, that faith without workes is no faith. And if a dead body, be notwithſtanding a true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, then according to <hi>S. James</hi> compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon here, a dead faith, is notwithſtanding a true faith, but yet not auaileable to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, becauſe it is dead: that is, becauſe it is onely faith, without good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And therefore it is a great impudencie in Heretikes, and a hard ſhift to ſay, that the faith of which the Apoſtle diſputeth all this while, is no true, or properly called, faith at al, it is the ſame faith, that <hi>S. Paul</hi> defined, and commended in all the 11. Chapter to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:7922:20"/>which is called the Catholike faith, and the ſame which being formed, and made aliue by charitie, iuſtifieth: Mary true it is, that it is not that ſpeciall faith, which the Heretikes fayne onely to iuſtifie; to wit, when a man doth firmly beleeue, as an Article of his faith, that himſelfe ſhall bee ſaued: This ſpeciall faith it is not, whereof the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh, for neither he, nor <hi>S. Paule,</hi> nor any other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred writer, in all the holy Scriptures, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake, or knewe of any ſuch forged faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>YOu would fayne build an argument vpon a ſimilitude: but you know ſuch ſimilitudes do rather illuſtrate then prooue a matter, and ſuch argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do either limpe, yea rather halt downe right, then runne roundly on al fower: Howſoeuer you pleaſe your ſelues in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring faith vnto the bodie, and good workes to the louſe: yet the wiſe and learned, haue rather likenet true faith to the ſoule, and good works to the bodie: for as the bodie hath no life of it ſelfe, but only of the ſoule: euen ſo works haue no life of themſelues, but only of faith. But a dead faith with you is a true faith, ſo is a fire
<pb facs="tcp:7922:20"/>without heate, a true, and a reall fire: of ſuch a faith <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſayth in this <hi>
                        <hi>Chapter. verſ. 19.</hi> Daemones credunt &amp; contremiſcunt:</hi> The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills beleeue, and quake for feare, if the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked without good workes haue a true faith, then the Deuill likewiſe hath a true and reall faith: you ſay it is great impudencie in Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, and a hard ſhift to ſay, that the faith of which the Apoſtle diſputeth, all this while, is no true, or properly called, faith at all. Let vs ſee whether this impudencie and hereſie may not bée caſt vpon Sainct <hi>Iames</hi> himſelfe by the euidence of his owne words: What auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth my Brethren, if a man ſay he hath faith, and hath no workes: <hi>Iacob. 2. verſ. 14.</hi> By this beginning it is not obſcure, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of faith Sainct <hi>Iames</hi> meaneth, placed in a certaine vayne vaunt of wordes, and not approoued by any workes: For that faith which hath no workes, is a fayned faith. But of that faith which wanteth workes <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, as it is cleere by the very wordes: wherefore it is manifeſt that the Apoſtle doth ſpeake here of a fayned faith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is more manifeſt of that which followeth. For he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of ſuch a faith, which doth not helpe the naked and poore, but in words &amp; wiſhes only: <hi>verſ. 15.</hi> Go in peace, warme you, and be you filled: &amp; yet performeth nothing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they deſire.
<pb facs="tcp:7922:21"/>This is a fayned faith, the which <hi>Iames</hi> alſo becauſe it wanteth deedes, he calleth it a dead faith: <hi>verſ. 16.</hi> Then he concludeth, that the ſame is a true faith, which can bee ſhewed by workes, when as the ſame is no ſuch faith: it followeth, that it is no true, but a dead and a ſayned faith. But that which he ſubioyneth, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away all doubt. For wilt thon be taught, what faith <hi>Iames</hi> doth denie to be <hi>effectula</hi> to righteouſnes and ſaluation <hi>verſ. 19.</hi> You may know that, of that, of theſe words: Thou doeſt beleeue that there is one God. Thou doeſt well: the Deuills beléeue and tremble. He ſpeaketh of that faith, which falleth into the Deuills themſelues. But that faith is faiued, counterfaite, and dead. Therefore this is that faith, whereby alone, <hi>Iames</hi> doth denie vs, to be iuſtified. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Booke <hi>
                        <hi>De fide &amp; operibus. cap. 14.</hi> Iames</hi> is greatly agaynſt thoſe which are ſo wife to thinke, that faith is auaileable to ſaluation without workes, that he compareth them to Deuills. Hereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that <hi>Sainct Auguſtine</hi> meant, that <hi>S. Iames</hi> meant not a true faith, except the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills faith be a true faith.</p>
                  <p>You adde further, that it is the ſame faith that <hi>S. Paule</hi> defined <hi>Hebr. 11.</hi> and the ſame that is called the Catholike faith. Oh how you miſtake the Scriptures: and being a
<pb facs="tcp:7922:21"/>faithles generation, doe not knowe what a true faith meaneth. Is this faith without workes, a true faith? Is this faith the ſame faith, which the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebr.</hi> doth meane: Why then was not the Deuil canonized among the Saincts? why was he not reckoned among <hi>Abel</hi> &amp; the reſt: By the vertue of that faith ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified by the Apoſtle, many were ſtoned, cut in ſunder, being killed with the ſword were ſlaine: they wandred vp &amp; downe in ſheepes cloathing, and goates ſkinnes, being deſtitute, oppreſſed, and euill intreated: <hi>Hebr. 11. verſ. 37.</hi> Therfore I maruell you are ſo ſhameleſſe, to affirme, that this faith, which <hi>S. Iames</hi> affirmeth to bée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Deuills, and that faith which in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebr.</hi> is made only proper to the Saincts, is all one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> true it is (ſay you) that it is not that ſpeciall faith, which the Heretikes fayne only to iuſtifie, to wit, when a man doth firmly beleeue, as an Article of his faith, that himſelfe ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: this ſpeciall faith it is not, whereof the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle here ſpeaketh; for neither he, nor <hi>S. Paule,</hi> nor any other ſacred writer in al the holie ſcriptures, euer ſpake, or knew of any ſuch forged faith.</p>
                  <p>You binde it ſolemnely with <hi>Mary,</hi> that it is not the ſpeciall faith, which the Heretikes fayne only: who be thoſe Heretikes: The Apoſtles trow we which (as the Creede, which hath their name) taught vs this ſpeciall faith: I beleeue in
<pb facs="tcp:7922:22"/>God the Father: and not wee beleeue. Or the Prophet <hi>Dauid Pſal. 63. verſ. 1.</hi> O God thou art my God, earely will I ſeeke thee, &amp;c. Or <hi>S. Auguſtine <hi>De ciuit. Dei. lib. 1. cap. 29. Deus meus, vbique praeſens eſt, vbi<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> totus, nuſquam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſus:</hi>
                     </hi> My God is euery where preſent, euery where whole, no where incloſed, or ſhut vp. Or it may be <hi>S. Paule</hi> is that ſpeciall Heretike, who doth ſpecially countenance this ſpeciall faith, <hi>Galat. 2. verſ. 20.</hi> I liue in the faith of the ſonne of God, which hath loued me, and hath giuen himſelfe for my ſake. Heare whether <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> bee not acceſſarie with him in this hereſie (as you call it) writing vpon <hi>Geneſ. Hom. 34. S. Paule</hi> ſayth, Chriſt hath loued me: O <hi>Paule,</hi> the benefite that is common to all, thou vſeſt as peculiar to thy ſelfe: yea verely, ſayth <hi>S. Paule,</hi> For albeit that ſacrifice were offered for al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, yet for the loue that I beare toward him, the thing that was done to all, I accoumpt as proper, and ſeuerall to my ſelfe alone. Thus the manner of the Prophets is to do, and ſay: O God my God: notwithſtanding he is the God of all the world: but this is ſpeciall and peculiar to loue, of things common to make things pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar. Thou ſaieſt, Chriſt hath loued me: what ſaieſt thou: Hath Chriſt loued thee only, and no man els: No (ſaith <hi>Paule</hi>) he hath loued al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: but I owe him thankes, as if he had loued me alone, &amp; had giuen himſelf only for me. Now
<pb facs="tcp:7922:22"/>by this time I think you ſée what cauſe of bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you haue (which lay impudencie to our charge) in ſaying, That neither <hi>S. Paule,</hi> nor any other ſacred writer in al the holy ſcriptures, euer ſpake, or knewe of any ſuch ſpeciall faith, which you call forged: becauſe in your Annotation vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>24. verſ.</hi> of this <hi>2. cap.</hi> you referre vs to the <hi>Rom. 2.</hi> I will ſet downe your owne wordes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Rhemists_annotations">
               <head>Rhemiſts Annot. Rom. 2. verſ. 13.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Not the hearers]</hi> This ſame ſentence agreeable to Chriſtes words, <hi>(Mat. 7.21.)</hi> is the ſame very ground of <hi>S. Iames</hi> diſputation, that not faith alone, but good works alſo do iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie. Therefore <hi>S. Paule</hi> (howſoeuer ſome peruerſly conſter his wordes in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) meaneth the ſame, that <hi>S. Iames.</hi> And here he ſpeaketh not properly of the firſt iuſtification, when an Infidel or ill man is made iuſt, who had no acceptable workes before, to be iuſtified by: (of which kind he ſpecially meaneth in other places of this Epiſtle) but he ſpeaketh of the ſecond iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or increaſe of former iuſtice, which he that is in Gods grace daylie proceedeth in, by doing all kind of good works, which be iuſtices; and for doing of which, he is iuſt in deede before God: and of this kind doth <hi>S. Iames</hi> namely treate. Which is directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Heretikes of this time, who not
<pb facs="tcp:7922:23"/>only attribute nothing to the workes done in ſinne and infidelitie, but eſteeme nothing at all, of all Chriſtian mens workes, toward iuſtification &amp; ſaluation, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demning them as vncleane, ſinfull, phariſaical, which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly agaynſt theſe &amp; other Scripture, and plaine blaſpheming of Chriſt and his grace, by whoſe ſpirit &amp; cooperation we do them. <hi>13. Shall be iuſtified]</hi> Of all other Articles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled by Heretikes, they vſe moſt guile in this of iuſtification: &amp; ſpecially by the equiuocation of certaine words, which is proper to all contentious wranglers, and namely in this word <hi>Iuſtifie.</hi> Which becauſe they finde ſometime to ſignifie, the acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a guiltie man of ſome crime, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee is in deede guiltie, and for which hee ought to bee condemned (as by mans iudgement, either of ignorance or of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, often a very malefactor is deemed or declared, and pronounced innocent.) They falſly make it to ſignifie in this place, and the like, whereſoeuer man is ſayd to bee iuſtified of GOD, for his workes or otherwiſe: as though it were ſaied, that God iuſtifieth man, that is to ſay, imputeth to him the iuſtifice of Chriſt, though he be not indeed iuſt: or of fauour reputeth him as iuſt, when indeed he is wicked, impious, and vniuſt. Which is a moſt blaſphemous
<pb facs="tcp:7922:23"/>doctrine againſt God, making him either ignorant who is iuſt, and ſo to erre in his iudgement, or not good, that can loue and ſaue him, whome he knoweth to be euil. And a maruelous pitifull blindnes it is in the Churches aduerſaries, that they ſhould thinke it more to Gods glory, and more to the commendation of Chriſtes iuſtice, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and mercy, to call and count an ill man ſo continuing, for iuſt, then by his grace and mercy, to make him of an ill one, iuſt indeed, and ſo truly to iuſtifie him, or as the word doth heere ſignifie, to eſteeme and approue for iuſt indeede, him that by his grace keepeth his lawe and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for that the keepers or doers of the commaundements be iuſt and ſo reputed, it is plaine by the correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer words, Not the hearers are iuſt, but the doers, whereupon <hi>S. Augustine de Sp. &amp; lit. ca. 26. tom. 3.</hi> hath theſe words, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaid, The doers of the law ſhalbe iuſtified: what other thing is ſaid then, The iuſt ſhall be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, for the doers of the law verely are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, for the doers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law verely are iuſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>YOu erre not knowing the Scriptures, for the Apoſtle in that <hi>Rom. 2. verſ. 13.</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that vniuerſall accuſation of man-kind, doth ſeuerally apply the ſame both to <hi>Gentiles</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:7922:24"/>
                     <hi>Iowes,</hi> and becauſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> gloried in the law, he vſeth a preuention againſt them, that the ſame law doth not excuſe them, but condemne them, becauſe not to heare the law, but to kéepe the law doth iuſtifie. We confeſſe a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which hé that is in Gods grace, dayly procéedeth in according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scripture, <hi>1. Iohn 3. verſ. 7.</hi> He which doth righteouſneſſe, is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, meaning, that they are not iuſt, which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from vices, but they whch do righteous things. See alſo in another place, <hi>Apoc. 22. verſ. 11. <hi>Qui iustus eſt, iuſtificetur adhuc.</hi>
                     </hi> He which is iuſt, let him be more iuſtified. We are not ignorant, that there is ſuch a righteouſnes, but we deny vtterly that by this righteouſnes we do obteine eternall life, the which, neither <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> nor <hi>Dauid,</hi> neither any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath obtained, but by faith imbracing Chriſt, as the Apoſtle in the Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> doth moſt manifeſtly declare: For by the works of the law, no fleſh is iuſtified, <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lath. 2. verſ. 16.</hi> Alſo in another place he ſaith, Bleſſed is that man, to whome righteouſnes is imputed, without works, <hi>Rom. 4. verſ. 6.</hi> If we attribute nothing to the works done in ſinne and infidelitie, I hope we haue the Apoſtle part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with vs, <hi>Rom. 14. verſ. 23.</hi> But whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is not of faith, is ſin: and <hi>Hebr. 11. verſ. 6.</hi> But it cannot be that any man can pleaſe him without faith: if to ward iuſtification and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:7922:24"/>we ſay Chriſtian mens works are nothing auaileable, we haue <hi>S. Paule</hi> to hold with vs, <hi>Gal. 2. verſ. 21.</hi> For if iuſtice be by the law, then Chriſt died without cauſe. Otherwiſe we ſay the works of the Godly to be the gift of God, to pleaſe God, and that a moſt ample and largere: ward is promiſed, and ſhall be performed vnto them. Yet that they are not perfect, as the law of God requireth, neither void of all fault, for that contagion of ſin which hath corrupted our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, neither can be vtterly extirped in this life. But the Lord doth ſo approue the Godly mens works, as he doth entertaine the Godly them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: For although Gods children do labour with many diſeaſes of ſin, notwithſtanding God doth loue them for Chriſtes ſake, ſo God doth allow our works, albeit not altogether perfect, he rewardeth them, &amp; teſtifiech that they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto him. But that any man ſhould ſay that the works of the Saincts are nothing but vncleane, ſinfull, phariſaicall, we neuer ſaid ſo: for in the Saincts and regenerate, there be moſt excellent gifts of the holy Ghoſt, as faith, hope, loue, patience, humblenes, meekenes, peace, ioy, tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, hatred of ſin, deſire of righteouſnes: theſe, &amp; ſuch like, God doth accept of in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and of mercy doth crowne his good gifts in them, <hi>Gregor. Moralium. lib. 9. cap. 14. Omnis humana iuſtitia, iniuſtitia eſſe conuincitur, ſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictè iudicetur,</hi> All mans righteouſnes is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced
<pb facs="tcp:7922:25"/>to be vnrighteouſnes, if it be narrowly iudged. In this article we vſe no deceit, neither guile, and are no more wranglers then the holy Scriptures &amp; holy Fathers. And the God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of your Schoolemen, <hi>Thomas. in Galat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. lect. 4. Opera non ſunt cauſa, canaliquis ſit iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us apud Deum, ſed potius ſunt executiones &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtationes,</hi> Works are not the chuſe why any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is iuſt before God, but rather the executions and manifeſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of iuſtice, ſee <hi>Aug. de verb. Apoſt. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 15. Hier. lib. 1. aduerſ. Pelagian. Bernard in Cantic. Ser. 73. Si iniquitates obſeruauerit,</hi> If he ſhall marke the iniquities, yea euen of the elect, who ſholbe able to abide it: And againe, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morabor iuſtitiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſolius, ipſa enim eſt mea, nem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, fact us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es mihi tu iuſtitia a Deo.</hi> I will make mention of thy righteouſnes only, for that it is mine, to wit, thowart made vnto me righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> God: The Apoſtle <hi>Acts. 13. verſ. 39.</hi> he ſaith that we are iuſected by Chriſt from all thoſe things firſt which we could not be iuſtified by the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> God doth not accompt him iuſt, or impute righteouſnes unto him, that ſtill continueth in his ſins<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your blindnes is great thats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cleere light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> thou ſhalt mark out iniquities, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lord, Lord, who ſhalbe able to abide? &amp; the ſame Prophet coueteth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to be bleſſed, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> without works, <hi>Pſalme 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Rom. 4. verſ. 6.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7922:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
